A Guide to the Papers of James Fenimore Cooper, 1826-1850
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of James Fenimore Cooper, 1826-1850
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6245-q
This collection consists of 24 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This item was purchased from the Seven Gables Bookshop on 15 February 1966.
Scope and Content Information
This collection of James Fenimore Cooper papers includes letters and invitations.
Contents List
- Letter from Cooper to Carey, Lea, and Blanchard 13 April 1838, ALS
  Cooper to Carey, Lea, Blanchard, regarding Homeward Bound and Home as Found.
- Letter from Cooper to Mrs. Peter A. Jay 15-20 September 1826, ALS
- Printed invitation to Cooper from MMe la Mise de Dolomieu 6 February 1831, TN
- Letter from [Cooper?] to Armand Carrel [7?] March 1832, ALS
  Cooper to Armand Carrel, for Le National (Paris), [missing 3/27/68].
- Letter (invitation) from...to Cooper 16 February 1835, ALS, 1 page.
- Letter from Cooper to M. Dubois (invitation) 3 March 1835
- Letter from ... to Cooper 25 September 1835, ALS
- Letter from Cooper to Lewis Gaylord Clark 12 July 1845, ALS
  Cooper to Lewis Gaylord Clark, regarding Bunker Hill in Lionel Lincoln.
  This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume V, 46.
- Letter from Cooper to Richard H. Dana, Sr. 30 October 1845, ALS, 2 pages. Blue Slipcase in Barrett Room mislabeled "Oct 20, 1845."
  Cooper to Richard H. Dana, Sr., lecturing to the Mercantile Library Association of Boston, regarding naval history.
  This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume V, 92.
- Letter from Cooper to George Robertson, Jr. 9 November 1846, ALS
  Cooper to Geroge Robertson, Jr., declining to lecture.
- Letter from Cooper to Horace Greenough 6 May 1847, ALS
  Cooper to Horace Greenough, introduction for W. W. Campbell. (Samuel F.B. Morse?), family affairs.
- Letter from Cooper to George P. Putnam 10 December 1847, ALS
  Cooper to George P. Putnam, regarding medal Cooper struck by Commodore Elliott after the Battle of Lake Erie controversy was settled. Mentions Mr. Adams and Hist. Soc. of R.I. [ca. 1848?] P.S. regarding Free Soil agitation, with Cooper autograph pasted on bottom.
- Letter from Cooper to John Fagan 19 October 1849, ALS
  Cooper to John Fagan, regarding financial and legal affairs.
- Letter from Cooper to John Fagan 7 March 1849, ALS
  Cooper to John Fagan, regarding new edition of The Spy. "The work must equal Irving's Sketch Book..." Important. Also Sea Lions.
  This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume VI, 15.
- Letter from Cooper to John Fagan 21 November 1849, ALS
  Cooper to John Fagan, mentions The Ways of the Hour, Red Rover, Pioneers, Mohicans, Prairie.
- Letter from Cooper to William Starbuck Mayo February 1850, ALS, typescript; original is pasted in book.
  Cooper to William Starbuck Mayo, regarding friends: Gen. Scott, Read, Kearny, Shubrick.
- Letter from Cooper to George P. Putnam [19?] June 1850, ALS
  Cooper to George P. Putnam, regarding Rural Hours.
  This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume VI, 195.
- Letter from Cooper to James Hackett 23 October 1850
  Cooper to James Hackett.
  This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume VI, 229.
- Letter from Cooper to Henry F.C. Atkins 13 December 1850, ALS, autograph.
  This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume VI, 247.
- Letter from Cooper to Mrs. [H] Fish 1 August n.y., ALS, autograph, 3 pages.
  Cooper to Mrs. [H] Fish, regarding personal and family news.
- Letter from Cooper to M. De Voraign ALS, in French, 1 page
- Letter from Charles Mathews to Cooper n.d., ALS
  Charles Mathews, actor, to Cooper, invitation. Signed "Mat."
- Letter to press on taxation n.d., AMs, 3 pages folio, with typescript and newspaper clipping
  Letter to press on taxation, Lafayette's opinions, etc. Newspaper clipping on Cooper's libel suit.
- Letter from Cooper to M. Dubois n.d., AN, 1 page.
  Cooper to M. Dubois, invitation.